howdy hey
any secrets you want to tell us
oh that got me two and a half years in
prison i should probably keep my mouth
shut
[Music]
what's life like as a spy oh jared it
was so much fun i miss it very much
actually
i got to see the world 65 countries
recruited nine spies over the years to
work for us
it was fun well let's get this part of
this story out of the way you were
actually
my high school teacher i was indeed
i was american government in american
history i do remember you because every
once in a while there's a teacher
who stands out who actually for some
reason or another
gets you to pay attention to listen so
thank you for that thank you that's very
kind of you
it's insane man this is a pretty weird
world to go from high school teacher to
international spy you know jared life
takes these very odd twists and turns
you just never know what's in store for
you
that last semester that i had you in
class i went to see the professor
and he said listen i ought to tell you
i'm not really a professor here i'm
actually undercover as a professor i'm a
senior cia officer would you be
interested in joining the cia
and i said
sure
hadn't really thought of it but i was
getting married soon after graduation i
had no job and i thought well this
sounds like fun
so next thing i know a few months later
i was in the cia
when i first arrived somebody met me at
the front gate and
they took me into an auditorium with
about 30 other people and i raised my
right hand and i swore to uphold the
constitution
i didn't swear to to you know keep the
agency's
crimes a secret but i swore to uphold
the constitution and and i meant it and
they put me to work on iraq and they
said the reason i was being assigned to
iraq was that nothing ever happened
there
so i had been there about nine months
and just as i begin to feel like i
really know what i'm talking about iraq
invades kuwait so next thing i know i'm
i'm going to the white house and
briefing the president and taking a call
at my desk from colin powell when he was
the national security advisor and then i
went into kuwait city with the marines
on liberation day march 1st 1991
i went through the whole traditional
clandestine operations training
guns
explosives counter-terrorism driving
jumping out of an airplane
swimming through a swamp to you know
make a dead drop on an island you're all
covered with leeches you have to fight
the
cotton mouths that are swimming across
the the bog
it was it was rough but one thing that i
was really really good at
was convincing people to commit treason
now oftentimes they'll want money but a
lot of times it's not about the money
they want their children to go to an
american university one guy wanted a new
vespa
i mean he was willing to commit treason
for me espionage in exchange for a vespa
one guy did it just because he loved the
united states so what happened after
that in the summer of 2000 there was an
attempt on my life in athens there was a
terrorist group there they planned to
kill me on the way to work one day but
they saw that i was in an armored car
and they knew from earlier surveillance
that i was carrying a weapon and so
instead they killed my next door
neighbor steven saunders who was the
british defense attache
so i was deemed to be a little bit too
hot meaning too many
of our enemies knew my true identity and
so i was pulled back from the middle
east and then september 11th hit
[Applause]
it was in pakistan as the chief of
counter-terrorism operations that i led
what became the biggest
counter-terrorism rate in cia's history
we captured abu zubaydah who we believed
at the time was the number three in
al-qaeda we picked him up and we threw
him into the back of a filthy toyota
pickup truck
and then he went to what ended up being
the first
cia secret prison
where is he now
he's in guantanamo now he's been in cia
custody for
almost 14 years now
he's not been charged with a crime i'll
add what are they waiting for
they can't legally charge him with a
crime because everything that he ever
told the cia was as a result of torture
they began with the most entry level of
the torture techniques they would grab
them by the lapels and shove them up
against a plywood wall and all that
stuff is humiliating but it's not
painful in any way but then things get
very serious very quickly after that
abu zabeda for example had an irrational
fear of cockroaches
and so they would keep him in a dog cage
and they would fill the cage with
cockroaches just to make him insane they
ended up waterboarding him 83 times
and
even after 83 times
he gave up no actionable intelligence he
saved no american lives he disrupted no
attacks against the united states the
torture just simply doesn't work
and so it was it was
a crime with no
outcome
that you can show the american people
actually helped anybody
there were techniques too jared that i
that i thought were worse than
waterboarding there was something called
the cold cell
where we strip a prisoner naked you
chain him to an eye bolt in the ceiling
so his arms are up and he can't get
comfortable he can't kneel or sit or lay
down his cell is chilled to 50 degrees
and every hour somebody goes in and
throws ice water on him that's illegal
we killed three people using that
technique but no one was ever charged
with a crime i mean the investigation
found that ah yep he died well
sorry too bad it was an accident we
can't lose who we are as americans
in the name of counterterrorism
you know we have civil liberties in this
country
and i want my september 10th country
back
i left the cia in 2004 i went into the
private sector
and i kept my mouth shut for five and a
half years
and in 2007 i got a call from brian ross
at abc news
so i went down to the abc news studio in
washington
brian ross flew in from new york
and i said three things in that
interview that utterly changed the
course of the rest of my life i said the
cia was torturing its prisoners
i said that torture was official u.s
government policy and i said the policy
was approved by
and signed by the president of the
united states
the cia was very angry with me for
airing the dirty laundry
and so they asked the justice department
to uh
to charge me
in january of 2012
i was charged with
three counts of espionage
for the abc news interview
now
the the point really was not to find me
guilty the point was to make an example
of me to deter other whistleblowers from
coming forward and the justice
department really has this down to a
science they know that your attorneys
are very expensive i had 11 attorneys
and i was looking at 45 years in prison
i said i'm not doing 45 minutes i'm
going to fight this i don't care what it
costs that's not really what your
defense attorneys want to hear and you
know we got up over a million bucks and
they said look i think we should
investigate the idea of a plea
and they said well what do you want us
to offer them i said tell them i'll do a
year and a day a year and a day would
make me eligible for early release at
ten and a half months
so we offered a year and a day and they
came back with three years
we went with two they said two and a
half
and they said it's our final offer so
what do you do i have five kids at home
do you roll the dice
knowing that the government wins 98.2
percent of its cases according to
propublica
i couldn't take that chance
so i took the deal
and then
just a couple of months later
my attorneys drove me up to prison
and dropped me off
anything that keeps you up at night
i'm not sure that we can trust our
government everything that the cia has
told us since 2001 has been a lie and it
doesn't matter who's in the white house
in august of this year 2015
the white house killed 424 people in
august
these are people who've never been
charged with a crime they've never faced
their accusers in court they've never
had their day to explain themselves
we're just supposed to take the cia's
word for it that these are bad people
but then we have these independent
voices human rights watch
amnesty international the international
committee of the red cross saying wait a
minute 90 of these people are innocent
civilians who just happen to be
near the site of these drone attacks
one of my attorneys is representing a
drone whistleblower right now
and he told me recently that
he was operating his drone from
a basin i think it was nevada or new
mexico he's connected by radio
and the guy in centcom says you see the
target
launch
and the guy said i can't launch there's
a child next to him
and the guy at centcom said it's not a
child it's a goat
and he said man i'm looking at it
it's a child
and he told him launch
but the guy said i couldn't launch that
thing and he didn't
well now he's facing court-martial
and possibly other charges including a
dishonorable discharge for refusing to
kill a child
i mean is this really where we want our
country to be
have we so turned our backs on civil
liberties since september 11th in the
name of national security it was a child
where americans were better than that
and it's not too late to turn this thing
around
ed snowden opened so many doors for
people around the world to discuss these
issues that courage
is just so rare and so special he risked
everything
and because
he did it in such a public fashion
the big guns were pulled out against him
and i told him
don't come home i said you won't get a
fair trial in the eastern district of
virginia your jury will be made up of
people from the cia fbi dod
homeland security and every intelligence
and defense contractor in washington i
said don't come home not until the
american people come to their senses and
realize what a national service you've
provided
what's the worst case scenario
the worst case scenario is that the
courts uphold
the ability of nsa to keep spying on
american citizens
and that nsa continues to build
facilities like the new one they have in
utah that has enough storage space to
record and hold every telephone call
text message and email from every
american citizen for the next 500 years
and that the american people don't
realize
what we're losing here in terms of our
civil liberties
you know there there are no
demonstrations in the street and i just
don't understand why that is
so the worst case scenario really is
that the american people don't come to
their senses in time to save the country
[Music]
you